Elihu Thomson Papers 1865-1944 Mss.Ms.Coll.74
American Philosophical Society
Elihu Thomson Papers
1865-1944
Mss.Ms.Coll.74
American Philosophical Society
65.0 Linear feet 65 linear feet
An electrical engineer, inventor, and entrepreneur, Elihu Thomson was an innovator in electrification in both a technical and corporate sense. With interests that ranged from the technical (electrical meters, high-pressure steam engines, dynamos, generators) to scientific (fused quartz optics, X-rays), Thomson acquired over 700 patents in his career, and in 1882, founded one of the early electrical corporations in the United States, the Thomson-Houston Company, which merged with the Edison Electric Company in 1892 to form the General Electric Company. The Thomson Papers are a massive and nearly comprehensive collection documenting the wide range of Thomson's scientific and technical interestsm from his electrical experiments, inventions, and patents, to his interests in astronomy, geology, and medicine, as well as his role in the development of two major corporations involved in electrification, the Thomson-Houston Electric Company and General Electric Company. Roughly three quarters of the collection is dated between 1890 and 1920 when Thomson was associated with General Electric, and was active in professional groups such as the American Institute of Electrical Engineers (AIEE), International Electrotechnical Commission. His research interests. The balance of the collection is comprised of eight boxes and five volumes relating to Thomson's patents; a series of notebooks kept at Central High School; 43 letterbooks, 1882-1936; diaries of trips to Europe; notebooks on genealogy; scrapbooks of cards, photographs, clippings, and other souvenirs; and 2 vols. of tributes on his eightieth birthday, etc.
Thomson, Elihu, 1853-1937
Bibliography
W. Bernard Carlson, Innovation as a Social Process: Elihu Thomson and the R ise of General Electric, 1870-1900 (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1991).
David O. Woodbury, Elihu Thomson, Beloved Scientist (Boston: Museum of Science, 1944)
John L. Haney, "The Elihu Thomson Collection," American Philosophical Society Yearbook 1944.
Separated Materials note
An extensive group of reprints was transferred to Printed Materials.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Thomson Papers have come to the APS Library in many accessions. The first group of papers were donated by Thomson's second wife, Mrs. Clarissa Hovey Thomson, after his death in 1937. Soon after, Owen D. Young, Chairman of the Board of General Electric, had Thomson's office files from the Lynn, Massachusetts plant transferred to the APS. Additional material was collected from Thomson's colleagues. Researchers interested in the history of the creation of this collection at the APS Library should see Series XV for further information.
In March of 1985, a second major accession from General Electric came to the APS Library. Approximately 3.5 linear feet, this material was sent from the G.E. Hall of History Foundation in Schenectady, New York. Prior to 1982, the papers had been housed in Thomson's personal office at the West Lynn (Massachusetts) plant. When the West Lynn plant was sold in 1982, the papers were transferred to the G.E. Hall of History. It appears that this second General Electric accession includes material pulled from the papers sent to the APS in 1937-38, due to proprietary interest held by G.E. at that time.
In September of 1980, W. Bernard Carlson of the University of Pennsylvania organized a conference at the APS in which the Thomson Papers were discussed and a planning report for their future arrangement and use was produced. Carlson used the collection heavily for his dissertation at the University of Pennsylvania (entitled Invention, Science, and Business: The Professional Career of Elihu Thomson, 1870-1900, 1984). Carlson subsequently developed this dissertation into a biography ( Innovation as a Social Process: Elihu Thomson and the Rise of General Electric, 1870-1900, Cambridge; New York: Cambridge University Press, 1991).
Scope and Contents note
The Elihu Thomson Papers (1853-1955) contain correspondence, subject files, manuscripts of published and unpublished works, speeches, notebooks, sketches, photographs, certificates, clippings, scrapbooks, and memorabilia which document Thomson's career as an inventor, electrical engineer, and entrepreneur. Thomson's original birth certificate from Manchester, England, is the earliest piece of the collection (1853). Some of the most recent items of the collection, primarily memorial pieces written by Thomson's colleagues and friends, date well after his death in 1937.
The collection spans Thomson's lifetime, with a significant amount of material dating from his high school years in Philadelphia, through his mid-career, and into his final years of retirement in Swampscott, Massachusetts. Thomson's many achievements in the development of late 19th and early 20th century technology as well as his involvement in the growth of the Thomson-Houston companies and the General Electric Company are the primary subjects of this collection.
The correspondence of Series I and II give a full understanding of Thomson's success in presenting his ideas on electricity, astronomy, physics, lightning, fused quartz, scientific education, investments, and patents. Thomson was a remarkably focused person who knew clearly that he was not interested in business administration or management and so removed himself from those elements as they developed from his scientific ideas and inventions. Thomson's work for the General Electric Company, through a combination of his ideas and the enormous professional respect he gained, was done on Thomson's own terms. He apparently did very much as he pleased, and was pleased first to be a scientist.
Thomson had a life-long reputation for kindness, honesty, good manners and charm, although the papers also reveal a kind of curtness in his early years. The papers reflect his privileged status among the corporate, professional and academic leaders of his time. It is not always clear where his activities were GE-related rather than simply the activities of Elihu Thomson the electrical engineer, the scientist, the professional. Added to this, the GE Company itself and Thomson and his professional peers apparently worked without clear boundaries as to where personal/professional interests and corporate interests started and stopped. They wrote about "personal" scientific questions on company letterhead and of course used informal names for professional celebrations, meetings, and congresses.
Consequently, keeping Series I (Professional Correspondence) and II (General Electric Company Correspondence) compartmentalized was a formidable task. These two series must be used together to gain a complete picture of Thomson's life and work, and they also serve as a "mortar," the subjects covered binding together all the other series.
The papers of Series III-XV offer a wide range of topics relating to Thomson's long life and career. His involvement in the development of early electric light and power systems, the growth of the modern research industry, the building of individual businesses, and the professionalization of engineers and their academic institutions is documented in the collection. Detailed information on Thomson's many inventions and patents is preserved through sketches, blueprints, photographs, notebooks, and manuscript comments. These documents involve early dynamos, three-phase generators, electric welding, transformers, meters, lamps, and steam engines. Besides information on Thomson's inventive process, researchers will also find material of note regarding his interests in astronomy, x-rays, and fused quartz optics.
The papers are divided into fifteen series:
Series I Professional Correspondence (52 boxes; 26 linear feet)
Series II General Electric Co. Correspondence (38 boxes; 19 linear feet)
Series IIa General Electric Letterbooks (44 volumes)
Series III Subject Files (7 boxes; 3.5 linear feet)
Series IV Published Works (manuscripts) (3 boxes; 1.5 linear feet)
Series V Unpublished Works (manuscripts) (2 boxes; 1 linear foot)
Series VI Speeches and Addresses (2 boxes; 1 linear foot)
Series VII Manuscripts and Transcripts of Works by Others (4 boxes; 2 linear feet)
Series VIII Notebooks (4 boxes; 2 linear feet)
Series IX Sketches (2 boxes; 1 linear foot)
Series X Comments on Patents (4 boxes; 2 linear feet)
Series XI Photographs (3 boxes; 1.5 linear feet)
Series XII Certificates (1 box; 0.5 linear feet)
Series XIII Newspaper Clippings and Scrapbooks (1 box; 0.5 linear feet)
Series XIV Memorabilia and Ephemera (1 box; 0.5 linear feet)
Series XV Material on the Creation of the Collection (2 boxes; 1 linear foot)
A. Correspondence
B. Inventories
Series XVI Oversized Materials (2 boxes; 0.5 linear feet)
Materials in oversized box #1 follow the same series arrangement as noted above. If an item is stored in this box, a note appears on the original folder in the standard sized boxes which refers researchers to oversized storage. Two large scrapbooks of Series XIII are located in oversized box #2.
Biographical/Historical note
Elihu Thomson (1853-1937) was an electrical engineer, inventor, business man, and entrepreneur who figured prominently in the development of early electric light and power systems in the United States. During a long career which spanned the 19th and 20th centuries, Thomson acquired over 700 patents involving dynamos, three-phase generators, repulsion induction motors, electric welding, transformers, meters, lamps, railways, and steam engines. Thomson was responsible for pioneering research in alternating currents and high frequency, as well as the first safety standards for electrical work. Additional studies in astronomy, refracting telescopes, optics, and x-rays enhanced his industrial research. Besides his achievements in early electric technology, Thomson made considerable contributions to the professionalization of engineers through his active involvement in organizations such as the Franklin Institute, the American Institute of Electrical Engineers, and the International Electrical Congress.
Elihu Thomson was born in Manchester, England on 29 March 1853 to Daniel Thomson and Mary Ann Rhodes Thomson. In 1858, the Thomson family moved to the United States and settled in Philadelphia. At the age of thirteen, Thomson entered Philadelphia's Central High School. Upon graduation in 1870, Thomson was offered a position with the school as an instructor in physics. By 1876, he was honored with the chair in chemistry.
In 1880, Thomson resigned from his professorship to enter the electric industry. He moved to New Britain, Connecticut to accept a position as an electrician with the American Electric Company. While employed with American Electric, Thomson developed his electric lighting system and formed the Thomson-Houston Company in 1882. In 1883, the Thomson-Houston works moved to Lynn, Massachusetts, where the great development of Thomson's electric company took place throughout the 1880s. The Thomson-Houston Electric Company merged with the Edison Electric Company of Schenectady, New York to form the General Electric Company in 1892. Major off-shoots of this company grew in Germany, France, and England and helped spread throughout Europe an electric lighting system based on Thomson's patents. Thomson's work was not restricted to the electric manufacturing business; he acted as president of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology from 1920 to 1923.
Thomson married his first wife, Mary Louise Peck, in 1884. They had four children: Stuart, Roland Davis, Malcolm, and Donald Thurston Thomson. His first wife died in 1916, and in 1923 he married Clarissa Hovey. Elihu Thomson died on 13 March 1937 after a long illness at his home in Swampscott, Massachusetts.
American Institute of Electrical Engineers; Ayrton, William Edward, 1847-1908; Barker, George Frederick 1835-1910; Barringer, Daniel Moreau, 1860-; Bragg, William Henry, Sir, 1862-1942; Brashear, John A. (John Alfred), 1840-1920; Bush, Vannevar, 1890-1974; Central High School (Philadelphia, Pa.); Coffin, Charles A., Jr.; Coolidge, William David, 1873-; Crompton, Robert E.; Cutter, George W.; De Forest, Lee, 1873-1961; Dercum, Francis X., (Francis Xavier), 1856-1931; Dunn, Gano, 1870-; Edison, Thomas A., (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931; Fleming, J. A., Sir, (John Ambrose), 1849-1945; General Electric Company; Greene, William Houston, 1853-1918; Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938; Hewitt, George Watson, 1841-1916; International Electrotechnical Commission; Jackson, Dugald C. (Dugald Caleb), 1865-1951; Jeans, James Hopwood, Sir, 1877-1946; Jeffcott, Henry Homan, d.1937; Johnson, Alba Boardman, 1858-; Keen, William W., (William Williams), b. 1837; Kennelly, Arthur E. (Arthur Edwin), 1861-1939; Langmuir, Irving, 1881-1957; Lovejoy, J. Robert; Mallinckrodt, Edward, 1845-1928; Martin, Thomas Commerford, 1856-1924; Meadowcroft, William Henry, 1853-1937; Mendenhall, Thomas Corwin; Miller, Dayton Clarence, 1866-1941; Morgan, Charles; Mottelay, Paul Fleury, 1841-; Pickering, William Henry, 1858-1912; Pratt, Joseph Hyde, 1870-1942; Pritchett, Henry S., (Henry Smith), 1857-1939; Rawle, Francis; Rice, Edwin Wilbur, 1831-1929; Riche, George W.; Shapley, Harlow, 1885-1972; Snyder, Monroe Benjamin, 1848-; Spooner, Henry John, 1856-1940; Steinmetz, Charles Proteur, 1865-1923; Stockley, George; Stratton, Samuel Wesley, 1861-1931; Stuart, George; Thompson, Maria M.; Thomson, Silvanus P.; Thomson-Houston Electrical Co.; Todd, David; Whitney, Willis Rodney, 1868-1958; Astronomy; Electrical equipment; Electrical experiments; Electricity; Geology; Inventors; Machinery, Electrical; Quartz optics; Steam engines; X-rays
- Series I. Professional Correspondence, Ca. 1870-1937; 52 boxes; 26 linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Letters arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent, mostly corporate correspondents such "Massachusetts Institute of Technology" or "American Institute of Electrical Engineers," but also some under the names of individual correspondents. Within the series are large sections of correspondence with Clarissa Hovey Thomson (Thomson's second wife), and also with John McManus, Jr., [identify]. As with any correspondent who has more than one letter in the series, the correspondence under those names are then arranged chronologically. In the cases where both persons corresponding were someone other than Thomson, both names were noted on the folder. In the cases of letters from institutions the name(s) of the individual representing the institution was also noted on the folder.
  - Aaron, Barney, 1915; 2 items (Box Series I-1)
  - Abakanowicz, B. Abdank, 1915; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Abbot, C. G., 1917-1927; 2 items (Box Series I-1)
    Smithsonian Institution
  - Abbott, Gordon, 1916; 6 items (Box Series I-1)
    Old Colony Trust Co.
  - Abrahams, B. A., 1888-1889; 2 items (Box Series I-1)
  - ABSE Bros., 1921; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Academie Française and Academie Des Beaux-Arts, 1916; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Academy of Natural Sciences. Peary Relief Committee, 1892; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Academy Round Table, 1929; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Acetylene Speciality Co., 1906; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Acheson, Edward G., 1907-1931; 5 items (Box Series I-1)
  - Acheson, E. G., Jr., 1931; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Acheson, E. G., Mrs., 1931; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Adams, Comfort A., 1903-1918; 9 items (Box Series I-1)
  - Adams, Edward D., 1923-1929; 8 items (Box Series I-1)
  - Adams, William Crittenden, 1912; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
    Union Mortgage Co.
  - Adirondack League Club, 1902-1920; 9 items (Box Series I-1)
  - Adkins, Ernest L., 1904; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Aeolian Co., 1916-1929; 6 items (Box Series I-1)
  - Aerial League of America, 1917; 3 items (Box Series I-1)
  - Aero Club of America, 1910; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Agassiz, G.R., 1906-1926; 6 items (Box Series I-1)
  - Agnew, P. G., 1916-1932; 4 items (Box Series I-1)
    Bureau of Standards
  - Aitken, E. S., 1913; 3 items (Box Series I-1)
    Trenton Potteries Co.
  - Akademja Gornicza W. Krakowie, 1927; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
    (Electrotechnical Inst. Of the Mining Academy
  - Alabama Polytechnic Institute, 1891; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Alaska Consolidated Copper Company, 1911-1914; 11 items (Box Series I-1)
  - Alaska Copper Corporation, 1913-1920; 12 items (Box Series I-1)
  - Alaska Copper Development Syndicate, 1915-1919; 3 items (Box Series I-1)
  - Alaska Copper Equipment Syndicate, 1914; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Albanese, G.S., 1927; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Alden, George I., 1916; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
    The Norton Co.
  - Alexander, Harry, 1903; 2 items (Box Series I-1)
  - Alexander, M. W., 1903-1931; 16 items (Box Series I-1)
    See also: National Industrial Conference Bd.
  - Alexander, Peter P., 1922; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Algonquin Club, 1902-1908; 2 items (Box Series I-1)
  - Allen, C. E., 1909; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Allen, Charles R., 1912-1913; 2 items (Box Series I-1)
    Massachusetts Board of Education
  - Allen, Frank, 1899; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Allen, Fred C., 1899; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Allen, H. W., 1900; 2 items (Box Series I-1)
  - Allen, James E., 1909; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Allen, John, 1909; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Allen, L. B., 1897; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Alley, Alonzo, 1904; 2 items (Box Series I-1)
  - Altoona Mechanic's Library, 1892; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
    From Chas B. Dudley, Pennsylvania Railroad Co.
  - Aluminum World and Brass and Bronze Industries, 1899; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Ambler American Asbestos Shingle & Sheathing Co., 1931; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - Amend, Otto P., 1927-1928; 2 items (Box Series I-1)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1888-1935; 24 items (Box Series I-1)
  - American Academy of Physiotherapy, 1925; 4 items (Box Series I-1)
  - American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1908-1925; 5 items (Box Series I-1)
  - American Agency for Hachette & Company, 1894; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
    Carl Schoenof
  - American Association For The Advancement of Science, 1897-1933; 23 items (Box Series I-1)
  - American Association of Electrotherapeutics and Radiology, 1919; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - American Association of Engineers, 1928; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - American Association of Inventors and Manufacturers, 1891-1902; 27 items (Box Series I-1)
  - American Association of Labor Legislation, 1911; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - American Association of Mechanical Engineers- Boston Section, 1920; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - American Association of Museums, 1925-1928; 2 items (Box Series I-1)
  - American Association to Promote the Teaching of Speech to the Deaf, 1911; 2 items (Box Series I-1)
  - American Astronomical Society, 1933-1934; 3 items (Box Series I-1)
  - American Automobile Club, 1902; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - American Automobile Directory, 1901; 1 item (Box Series I-1)
  - American Baptist Home Mission Society, 1891; 1 item (Box Series I-2)
  - American Bell Telephone Company, 1893; 2 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Blower Company, 1914; 1 item (Box Series I-2)
  - American Blue Book, 1913-1921; 3 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Button Fastener Company, 1891-1892; 3 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Ceramic Society, 1931; 2 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Chemical Society, 1899-1932; 23 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Colleges and Universities, 1905; 1 item (Box Series I-2)
  - American Congress of Radiology, 1933; 5 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Construction Council, 1922; 1 item (Box Series I-2)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1920; 1 item (Box Series I-2)
    Louis H. Gray
  - American Council on Education, 1933; 1 item (Box Series I-2)
  - American Cyanamid Company, 1916-1917; 3 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Defense League, 1916; 1 item (Box Series I-2)
  - American Defense Society, 1917; 2 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Economic Association, 1911-1912; 3 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Electric Light Association, 1906; 1 item (Box Series I-2)
  - American Electrical War Committee for France, 1917-1918; 7 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Electrical Works, 1897-1900; 3 items (Box Series I-2)
    Eugene F. Phillips
  - American Electrician, 1896-1898; 9 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Electrochemical Society, 1903-1928; 12 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Electro-Therapeutic Association, 1894-1929; 39 items (Box Series I-2)
    See also: Clarence Edward Skinner
  - American Forestry Association, 1906-1920; 8 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Free Art League, 1906; 2 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Geographical Society of New York, 1912; 1 item (Box Series I-2)
  - American Institute, 1929-1931; 2 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers, 1889-1897; 43 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers, 1898-1899; 34 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers, 1990-1902; 39 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers [Event honoring Marconi], 1902; 1 item (Box Series I-2)
    Elihu Thomson Characterization
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers, 1903-1906; 38 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers, 1907-1909; 23 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers, 1910-1912; 36 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers, 1913-1916; 43 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers, 1917-1922; 34 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers, 1923-1937; 40 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers. Lynn Section, 1914-1917; 10 items (Box Series I-2)
    G.M. Campbell
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers. Pittsfield Section, 1910-1913; 7 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers. Schenectady Section, 1909-1916; 15 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers. Standards Committee, 1898-1919; 16 items (Box Series I-2)
  - American International Corporation, 1921; 1 item (Box Series I-3)
  - American Journal of Roentgenology and Radium Therapy, 1932; 2 items (Box Series I-3)
  - American Journal of Science, 1900; 1 item (Box Series I-3)
  - American Law List, 1911; 1 item (Box Series I-3)
  - American Lead Pencil Company, 1909; 1 item (Box Series I-3)
  - American Legion, 1922-1931; 3 items (Box Series I-3)
  - American Library Association, 1898; 1 item (Box Series I-3)
  - American Loan and Trust Company, 1899; 3 items (Box Series I-3)
  - American Machinist, 1902; 2 items (Box Series I-3)
  - American Manual Training Association, 1896; 2 items (Box Series I-3)
  - American Metric Association, 1917; 2 items (Box Series I-3)
  - American Museum of Natural History, 1906-1934; 7 items (Box Series I-3)
  - American Museum of Safety, 1913; 1 item (Box Series I-3)
  - American Museum of Safety Devices and Industrial Hygiene, 1908; 1 item (Box Series I-3)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1876-1926; 28 items (Box Series I-3)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1927-1929; 34 items (Box Series I-3)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1930-1939; 20 items (Box Series I-3)
  - American Physical Society, 1900-1938; 28 items (Box Series I-3)
  - American Physical Therapy Association, 1931; 1 item (Box Series I-3)
  - American Press Association, 1897; 2 items (Box Series I-3)
  - American Projectile Company, 1892; 3 items (Box Series I-3)
  - American Publishing Company, 1902; 1 item (Box Series I-3)
  - American Rights League, 1916; 1 item (Box Series I-3)